A Guide to the Papers of the Randolph Family of Edgehill and Wilson Cary Nicholas,
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series I: Wilson Cary Nicholas Papers
    - 1811 November 28 W[illiam] A. Burwell to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses the growing anxiety in the country with the prospect of war with Great Britain and an understanding that Wilson Nicholas probably shares this unease, so Burwell tries to explain why such action may be necessary. Closes by asking Nicholas to provide money that he owes, 3 pages (Box-folder 2:75)
    - 1811 December 01 S[amuel] Smith to Wilson Cary Nicholas, indicates that enclosed is a title for the sale of 255 acres of land to Henry Clay which Nicholas must sign. Continues to discuss the financial issues surrounding George Nicholas's children and Owings, 3 pages (Box-folder 2:76)
    - 1811 December S[amuel] Smith to Wilson Cary Nicholas, minimally revised copy of 1811 December 1 letter, 3 pages (Box-folder 2:77)
    - 1812 January 09 John Hollins to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses a payment of $3000. Discusses the success of Commodore [John] Rodgers in opposition to some British vessels. Describes patriotic feelings for America, 3 pages (Box-folder 2:78)
    - 1812 February 03 D[abney] Carr to [Wilson Cary Nicholas?], informs that mail should be directed to Richmond not Charlottesville as his living arrangements have changed, 1 page (Box-folder 2:79)
    - 1812 February 03 J. Preston to [Wilson Cary Nicholas], expresses thanks for Nicholas's concern and wishes that he was not going out of office so that he could show his thanks, 2 pages (Box-folder 2:80)
    - 1812 March 19 Wilson Miles Cary to [Wilson Cary Nicholas], responds to a request about transactions that have been so long-standing that Wilson Cary can no longer remember what they were for precisely. Inquires after Wilson Nicholas's daughter and says that Nelson Nicholas is excelling in his studies of mathematics, 1 page (Box-folder 2:81)
    - 1812 March 20 Wilson Miles Cary to [Wilson Cary Nicholas], expresses some confusion in regards to a request for papers of Wilson Nicholas's brother [George?], 1 page (Box-folder 2:82)
    - 1812 April 03 Lewis Nicholas to [Wilson Cary Nicholas], asks for $30 to be sent to Peter Carr whom Lewis owes. Thanks Wilson Nicholas for about $150 previously given, 1 page (Box-folder 2:83)
    - 1812 May 03 John Nicholas to Wilson Cary Nicholas, requests that Wilson Nicholas pays Mrs. Johnson's interest of $385 as soon as possible. Continues to catch up on other business and familial issues, 3 pages (Box-folder 2:84)
    - 1812 May 15 Wilson Cary Nicholas to [?], draft fragment, discusses America's options in relation to the current war between Great Britain and France, suggesting that the war is forcing American minds against the government. The question, in Nicholas's mind, is whether it is better for America to go to war against one [Great Britain] or both of the countries, 4 pages (Box-folder 2:85)
    - 1812 May 27 J. Preston to [Wilson Cary Nicholas], discusses the payment of $3000 and possible places for relocation, 2 pages (Box-folder 2:86)
    - 1812 June 19 General Mason to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses a business transaction of pork at $16 per item and the price of salt, 3 pages (Box-folder 2:87)
    - 1812 August 22 J. Nicholas to Wilson Cary Nicholas, writes to follow up on Mrs. J[ohnston]'s interest that he inquired after last year and which he still has not received. Discusses the war with Great Britain, expecting there to be an early peace. Includes a bill of account, 3 pages (Box-folder 2:88)
    - 1812 June 25 General Mason to Wilson Cary Nicholas, informs Nicholas that he got the contract for pork at $16. Goes on to say that the Secretary of the Navy will write soon with details on the contract, 1 page (Box-folder 2:89)
    - 1812 August 23 General Mason to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses and works out a delay in the business contract on pork for the Secretary of the Navy, 1 page (Box-folder 2:90)
    - 1812 September 06 Edmund Randolph to [Wilson Cary Nicholas], discusses an unauthorized sale of slaves, 1 page (Box-folder 2:91)
    - 1812 September 17 Thomas Fairfax to [Wilson Cary Nicholas], asks for information about "your brother's youngest child, who I am informed is a daughter named (I believe) Kitty aged 14 or upwards." He also inquires about the number of children in his family and that of his brother, John. He asks Nicholas to visit him when he goes to Washington., 2 pages (Box-folder 2:92)
    - 1812 October 23 General Mason to Wilson Cary Nicholas, writes to follow-up on the pork contract, 2 pages (Box-folder 2:93)
    - 1812 October 25 General J. Marshall to [Wilson Cary Nicholas ?], has just returned from his expedition to the west to investigate opportunities for practical navigation routes between the Atlantic and the western states. He has not seen the reports of Mr. Gallatin, nor that of the New York commissioners, and asks if Nicholas has them and would loan them to him. Expects the Lexington gentlemen and Colonel Lewis to send him their sentiments soon., 2 pages (Box-folder 2:94)
    - 1812 October 26 Philip Nicholas to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses the upcoming sale of the [Peyton?] Randolph slaves scheduled for November 20 th in Richmond. Believes that a sale in Charlottesville would have been better, 3 pages (Box-folder 2:95)
    - 1812 November [?] Charles Everett to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses a personal controversy with someone, family business and personal affairs, 3 pages (Box-folder 2:96)
    - 1812 December 10 W[illiam] [Branch] Giles to W. C. Nicholas, wishes that he could say something complimentary about the financial situation but cannot because "even the splendid financial talents of the Secretary of the Treasury [Albert Gallatin], afford us no relief in his department. Instead of presenting to Congress a regular system of taxation, coequal and coextensive with the objects of the war, he has substituted a miserable impracticable attempt to plunder the merchants. The attempt too, is as destitute of principle, as it is of policy.", 3 pages (Box-folder 2:97)
    - [1812] Wilson Cary Nicholas to [ ? ], discusses the objectives of the 'present war' with Great Britain and the national and civic duty of Americans to defend their country and property, 8 pages (Box-folder 2:98)
    - 1813 January 03 Thomas Fairfax to [Wilson Cary Nicholas?], expresses concern in not hearing back from Nicholas after sending him a letter wanting information about the affairs of George's youngest child, 1 page (Box-folder 2:99)
    - 1813 January 09 Edmund Randolph to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses a property transfer involving [his daughter?] "dear Edmonia.", 1 page (Box-folder 2:100)
    - 1813 January 29 John Preston to [Wilson Cary Nicholas?], thanks Nicholas for the receipt of a payment for $1000, 1 page (Box-folder 2:101)
    - 1813 February 28 John Smith to [Wilson Cary Nicholas?], discusses the political environment and praises the performance of Nicholas in that realm. Mentions DeWitt Clinton's eagerness to become Lt. Governor in New York where his popularity is fading among both Federalists and Republicans. Discusses the method of farming on Long Island, saying that each locality has its own particular differences; discusses labor saving devices, especially the horse rake, now in general use on Long Island., 5 pages (Box-folder 2:102)
    - 1813 May 28 James Morrison to Wilson Cary Nicholas, provides news after a hiatus of seven months from home. Mostly revolves around the health and career prospects of friends and family. Asks about Colonel Owings' debts and whether or not any movement has been made on them, 3 pages (Box-folder 2:103)
    - 1813 June 29 R.C. Nicholas to [Wilson Cary Nicholas?], writing from Fort George, discusses the military situation at [Lake Ontario?] and the fact that the Americans are still on the defensive hoping to win possession of the Lake; a detachment went out under the command of Lt. Colonel [Boerstler?] and was defeated about eight miles above Queenston during the Battle of Beaver Dams. Believes a lot of the sickness in camp resulted from a lack of medical and hospital stores. "The hardships and privations are many, the chance of honors very few." He also hopes that the government will not have Coles succeed Colonel Parker in the Command of the 12 th Regiment., 4 pages (Box-folder 2:104)
    - 1813 July 27 John Hollins to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses some financial exchange and then continues to talk about domestic and international political and military affairs, relaying information that France, Russia, and Prussia have made peace. Informs Nicholas that since the British fleet has made its way down the Potomac, it is probably going to make them a visit again, 3 pages (Box-folder 2:105)
    - 1813 August 06 J. Preston to [Wilson Cary Nicholas?], indicates that Preston has been waiting on the banks of the Potomac for the British fleet for twenty days under the command of Admiral Warren, but was unable to obtain an "interview" with any of the gentlemen. Continues to discuss personal business, 1 page (Box-folder 2:106)
    - 1813 December 14 James Morrison to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses the affairs and position of 'our young friend Mr. N. Nicholas' who he fears has not lived up to his full potential and may continue to make poor and destructive decisions. Continues to speak of other business, family and personal affairs, especially some of the impact of the war upon his business affairs, 4 pages (Box-folder 2:107)
    - 1814 February 06 James Morrison to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses financial affairs and the shameful conduct of Cary and Nelson Nicholas in gambling and [drinking?] at length., 3 pages (Box-folder 2:108)
    - 1814 February 17 J. Preston to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses previous mail exchanges, touches on business, and closes with a short discussion of the current state of the war, 2 pages (Box-folder 2:109)
    - 1814 May 29 James Morrison to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses some family matters briefly. Indicates that Owings has paid $13,050. Writes that Cary and Nelson Nicholas have returned with Mrs. Bartlett, and the former will be a cripple for life due to a bad ankle., 1 page (Box-folder 2:110)
    - 1814 June 10 P. Randolph to [Wilson Cary Nicholas?], discusses the sale of a slave named William, requesting that the receiver make the sale in his county as prices will be higher. Continues to touch upon some domestic and international affairs briefly, 2 pages (Box-folder 2:111)
    - 1814 August 28 Wilson Cary Nicholas writes a memorandum to his executor, discusses the need for a sound book-keeper because Nicholas is uncomfortable with his capabilities, 1 page (Box-folder 2:112)
    - 1814 September 16 Wilson Cary Nicholas to [T.J.?] Randolph, brief discussion of personal matters; the back details the purchase of Pantops for $11,000, 2 pages (Box-folder 2:113)
    - 1814 November 2 Joseph C. Cabell to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses banking and an election coming up next week very briefly, in which he is certain that Nicholas will be elected by a considerable majority, 1 page (Box-folder 2:114)
    - [1814 December?] Wilson Cary Nicholas to Gentlemen, draft, fragment, refers to the time as one filled with terror and fear and that therefore he takes his entrance into a new office [Governor of Virginia?] with particular care and concern, 1 page (Box-folder 2:115)
    - 1815 January 29 Judge W. Brockenbrough to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses whether the Council has the constitutional and legal right or obligation both to advise the executive—in this case the governor—on candidates for appointment and also to nominate candidates. He believes that they should be able to do both because without such ability they would have almost no power in the government, 2 pages (Box-folder 3:1)
    - 1815 February 01 Maria Page to [Wilson Cary Nicholas?], requests that the recipient, who was an old friend, help her second son, Robert Page, to secure a military commission. He was a former student of medicine who had been called out for militia duty last summer in Alexandria, 2 pages (Box-folder 3:2)
    - 1815 February 15 Robert Taylor to [Wilson Cary Nicholas?], discusses the present state of the military force, their strengths and weaknesses, and gives an estimate of where more attention will need to be given. With list of officers enclosed, 8 pages (Box-folder 3:3)
    - 1815 April 11 George Hairston to Charles Johnston, informs him that the first court held in Henry County was on Monday, January 20 th, 1777. The session resulting in the division of the county begin in October 1776, 1 page (Box-folder 3:4)
    - 1815 March 29 S[amuel] Smith to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses financial information concerning George Nicholas's estate, Owings' debt, and Wilson Nicholas's involvement. Suggests that Owings has paid his debt in full and is now being taken advantage of. Advises Wilson Nicholas to settle and close his concerns with George Nicholas's estate, 3 pages (Box-folder 3:5)
    - 1815 April 25 Wilson Cary Nicholas to General Samuel Smith; Wilson Cary Nicholas to Colonel James Morrison, DRAFTS, discuss the financial business relating to Owings and George Nicholas's estate. Wilson Nicholas spends a good bit of time defending and justifying his actions in regard to Owings. Instructs Morrison to carry on his financial undertakings, 4 pages (Box-folder 3:6)
    - 1815 April 29 Ch[arles] Johnston to Wilson Cary Nicholas, provides a response to Nicholas's request for information concerning "certain persons who claimed Lands for military service rendered during the Revolutionary war." Only one of the parties is recollected, "Mr. Reynolds, who it is remembered, served as an officer in the army.", 1 page (Box-folder 3:7)
    - 1815 August 25 Spencer Roane to Elizabeth Roane, briefly informs of travels on rough roads and under tight time pressures, 2 pages (Box-folder 3:8)
    - 1815 September 28 S. Smith to Wilson Cary Nicholas, brief discussion of their joint financial debts and payments; Smith declares that he is quit of his debts, 1 page (Box-folder 3:9)
    - 1815 October 02 Nelson Nicholas to Wilson Cary Nicholas, apologizes for the twelve month hiatus in communication and explains his lapse in behavior and writing. Describes his desire to practice law in Kentucky and how he was led astray to indulge in frivolities which wasted his time, gave him a bad reputation, and embarrassed him so greatly that he did not feel that he should write. Says that he is now giving up on those activities and will redirect his life, 4 pages (Box-folder 3:10)
    - 1815 October 16 S[amuel] Smith Nicholas to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses Nelson Nicholas's decision to move from Kentucky to Louisiana to start anew but his inability to do so because he lacks the necessary funds. S. Smith Nicholas suggests that Nelson receive whatever interest had accrued upon his portion of Mrs. Fairfax's legacy, to provides funds for Nelson's move to Louisiana, 2 pages (Box-folder 3:11)
    - 1815 November 19 James Morrison to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses his past travels and gives brief news from his home before he leaves for Baltimore and Philadelphia in the next day or two, 3 pages (Box-folder 3:12)
    - 1815 December 15 Wilson Cary Nicholas, Jr. to Wilson Cary Nicholas, Sr., provides a thorough description of the result of his business at Warren, where he bought, and sold hogs, wheat, corn, meal, etc. A rather thorough description of his activities at the fair and explanations of why he bought what he did, 3 pages (Box-folder 3:13)
    - 1815 December 25 Wilson Cary Nicholas to Senators and Representatives in Congress from Virginia, requesting their support of William Wirt and John Chew, Commissioners appointed to settle the accounts of the Commonwealth with the Unites States, 2 pages (Box-folder 3:14)
    - [c. 1814-1815?] Wilson Cary Nicholas to [ ? ], draft fragment, discusses the recommendation of a member of the Council that General [John Hartwell] Cocke's Brigade be discharged due to the danger of epidemic disease spreading and the improbability of the enemy making an attack at this season of the year. However, Nicholas has received the report of Cocke about the condition of his men with no deaths in the last twelve days, and he has decided not to discharge that brigade. The conditions at Charles City Courthouse were severe enough that he has decided to discharge those troops because of a "dangerous and unknown fever." He has received reports that the British forces at St. Mary's are estimated between 1,000 to 3,000 men and that they have reports that between 8,000 to 10, 000 British troops have disembarked at New Orleans, and believes that Virginia cannot afford to diminish its defense forces, 4 pages (Box-folder 3:15)
    - [1814-1815] [Wilson Cary Nicholas] to [James Madison?], draft fragment, notes that most of American citizens are agriculturalists, discusses the War of 1812, questions about neutral rights and the actions of Great Britain. Believes that if Great Britain refuses to agree to a treaty with the United States, it means that they plan to colonize the states, take part of our territories, or force us to relinquish our fisheries. Considers the French—the problems with their Revolution and the resurgence of the monarchy with [Napoleon Bonaparte?] "the late Emperor of France made the parade of being elected consul for life & then Emperor by the suffrage of the people"; Urges for increases to be made to the militia to prevent problems especially because in Europe there are examples of counter revolutions. Mentions problems with [Northwest Territories?], due to their views on the current war, 4 pages (Box-folder 3:16)
    - 1816 April 23 Robert Scott to Wilson Cary Nicholas, briefly advises Nicholas on his progress in selling Nicholas' bills and closing the payments for pork for the current year and urges him to make his arrangements for next year's pork now and establish a credit for his bills in Philadelphia as opposed to Baltimore. Reverse contains Nicholas's statement of account with Scott for the purchase of hogs in Kentucky, 2 pages (Box-folder 3:17)
    - 1816 May 09 Wilson Cary Nicholas to [?]. discusses the closure of his account with Morrison and other financial business relating to the settlement of his brother's estate and the support of his family, and his concern that Mr. Morrison not be penalized for all the work he has done on behalf of the estate and his sister-in-law, 5 pages (Box-folder 3:18)
    - 1816 June 05 W[illiam] Coleman to Wilson Cary Nicholas, asks for the half year's interest on their bond, 1 page (Box-folder 3:19)
    - 1816 July 28 Wilson Cary Nicholas to Robert B. Taylor, draft, notifies Taylor of his appointment by Nicholas to be a judge of the General Court, 1 page (Box-folder 3:20)
    - 1816 September 04 Robert Carter Nicholas to W. C. Nicholas, Jr., thanks for the last letter and continues to discuss his thoughts of his current location in Leghorn, Italy. He recommends the country for many to consider visiting and moving to. Much of the letter concerns personal relations, particularly the education of Casario, and Robert urges his friend Wilson, on his visits to Staunton, "to inquire into his situation and to see that his master performs what he has engaged to do, especially in relation to his education,", 6 pages (Box-folder 3:21)
    - 1816 September 22 W[illiam] H. Cabell to [Wilson Cary Nicholas?], apologizes for being unable to ride down to Warren as the last letter requested due to the high water of the James. Promises that John Gamble, his attorney at the Farmers Bank will endorse his note for him. Cabell has also lost a good portion of his small tobacco crop due to frost, 2 pages (Box-folder 3:22)
    - 1816 October 03 R[obert] Smith to [Wilson Cary Nicholas?], discusses a proposal that the receiver sent concerning ways to dispel some financial debt; J.H. is going to Richmond to procure an exact statement as to the extent of his debt and names of his creditors; also informs him that G.P.S. is also bankrupt, 3 pages (Box-folder 3:23)
    - 1816 November 04 W[illiam] H. Cabell to Governor [Wilson C.] Nicholas, indicates receipt of request and confirms that he will oblige, 1 page (Box-folder 3:24)
    - 1816 November 29 S[amuel] Smith to Wilson Cary Nicholas, indicates that he disagrees with James Morrison and Nicholas that Owings has not yet paid his debt and interest in full; urges Nicholas to release Owings from the debt, 2 pages (Box-folder 3:25)
    - 1816 December 02 Wilson Cary Nicholas to [Samuel Smith?], draft, fragment, expresses disagreement with the recipient about Mr. Owings' having released himself from the debt he owes Nicholas. This disagreement surrounds the collection of interest within the arrangement, 6 pages (Box-folder 3:26)
    - 1817 January 07 John Cropper to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses the proper way to plant and tend beans and peaches, in regard to bags of bean seed and peach stone that were delivered to Nicholas, 2 pages (Box-folder 3:27)
    - 1817 February 16 James Morrison to Wilson Cary Nicholas, expresses his belief that Owings still owes money and that Nicholas and Smith should push for it with any means possible to prevent going into litigations for the money. Recommends giving power of attorney to himself and Robert Wickliffe to fully settle all his business in Kentucky, 7 pages (Box-folder 3:28)
    - 1817 February 18 S[amuel] Smith to Wilson Cary Nicholas, refers to an absent enclosed letter. Indicates that he finds Morrison's latest plan acceptable but that he believes that Owings does not owe the full portion of his bond to Smith, 1 page (Box-folder 3:29)
    - 1817 July 08 James Morrison to Wilson Cary Nicholas, relates a dream that Morrison had of Nicholas who was in a terrible situation and very depressed for he had to give his property to his creditors. In the dream, none knew about Nicholas's present situation, which had been his design. Goes on to give brief details of the current situation with Owings, 3 pages (Box-folder 3:30)
    - 1817 July 23 T. M. Randolph to [Wilson Cary Nicholas?], informs Nicholas that Randolph has drawn on his funds for several hundred dollars that day, 1 page (Box-folder 3:31)
    - 1817 August 05 Thomas M. Randolph to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses familial financial transactions. Refers to checks which were enclosed by B. Peyton to Jefferson, for his signature, having reached him, 3 pages (Box-folder 3:32)
    - 1817 September 10 W[illiam] Jones, President of the United States Bank, to Wilson Cary Nicholas, considers a proposal made by Nicholas in a previous letter to purchase the building in which the Bank of Virginia is currently housed. Continues to discuss possible avenues of financing such a venture, and remarks "the banking system has become extremely complicated in the United States,", 3 pages (Box-folder 3:33)
    - [1817] Wilson Cary Nicholas to William Jones, draft, discusses Nicholas's duties as [president of the Richmond branch of the Second Bank of the United States] to appoint a bank that would serve Virginia adequately, 4 pages (Box-folder 3:34)
    - [c. 1817] Wilson Cary Nicholas to William Jones, President of the U.S. Bank, two draft fragment letters. The letters both discuss the financial breakdown and upcoming court cases surrounding the U.S. Bank and the Virginia Bank, proposing possible actions to be taken, 5 pages (Box-folder 3:35)
    - [c. 1817] Wilson Cary Nicholas to William Jones, draft, discusses the uses of banks and reasons why new banks should open and the sort of precautions that should be taken with them, 3 pages (Box-folder 3:36)